Okay, we're going to call the order of the regular meeting of the Miami City Council for today's date and time.
Item 2 is the Congress Miami Hospital Centennial Recognition Proclamation.
And I told John and Simone that I wasn't going to read the whole thing and I'm not, but there are a couple of things
I would like to touch on because I was sitting there reading and saying, wow, for myself.
So this is a proclamation declaring July 1, 2019, this is the Congress Miami Hospital Centennial Recognition in the City of Miami.
Or as the Congress Miami Hospital established on July 11, 2019, it's just short of a hundred years.
As the Miami Baptist Hospital, it'll provide quality health care in the work of East Oklahoma while providing service with a heart.
They continued their commitment for over a century.
Their, as the Congress is the largest Oklahoma home, not for profit system.
The Congress Miami Hospital today provides over $48 million.
For the economic benefit to northeastern Oklahoma each year, I think that's something that most people don't realize when they think about a hospital.
And they know what the hospitals are and they go there if they don't realize the economic impact it has.
The other thing I think is significant, and I would all appreciate, the Congress Miami is a best in more than 20 million in capital improvements in the last 10 years.
That's really meaningful.
And we appreciate the Congress Board support.
We're not there for being resolved.
The mayor's shows in the Miami City Council.
Do you hear about it?
I declare to you, July 11, 2019, this is the Congress Miami Hospital Centennial Recognition and the City of Miami.
Okay, guys, want to come up?
Will we present this?
Will we?
Are you feeling pictures?
I don't know.
Do we have to see what will happen to you?
That's nice to have on town people leading the charge there.
We appreciate that.
Sure.
Your Honor, if I could just say something about yours very quickly.
I think on your next agenda, we're going to have an honorary street naming.
I believe it's C, Saudis.
That is really becoming the main entrance into a tapered from C, the owns Boulevard.
And we're going to call it a take or sweat.
That will be the third honorary street name that we've done.
And I believe the 30th is going to be the celebration, June 30th.
So, I think, I know Steve and I are both on the Integra Sport and we're really looking forward to that as well.
So, we have to be on it tonight.
It's going to be a good community celebration.
So, this is just the beginning with the resolution.
All right.
Thank you, again, gentlemen.
So, Terry, we appreciate it very much.
Item 3 is public hearing.
proposed FY-2019-2020 budget is public hearings call for any member of the public to present
to the governing body comments recommendations or information on any part of the proposed
budget.
So I'm going to declare this public hearing open at this time and invite anyone that has comments
or recommendations to come up to the podium and share those with us if they're already.
There being none.
I'm going to declare the public hearing closed.
We'll be taking it.
Anybody?
Sure.
I'm going to address the problem of utilities being heard about for flooded people and people
that don't flood.
And they, the city, I have learned that you've never had, I've served skilled and unskilled
people, disconnect things, use of the links from high attention, wires, and we're not probably
trained to do so.
And we use everybody on hand.
And I'm a plan.
And I've been through many blood and I don't want to do to prepare and be grateful.
And so I also go to the city and in the airs office, I asked them, what do you want me to do to
get my electric back home?
Because any blood that can be compared to that you have electricity to be able to get your house dry
back down.
Without it, you're just creating more mold and dry.
So, every time we go down there and they study well, we will send somebody out.
If you don't clean down, we'll turn it back home, especially if I haven't been in there.
And then eventually, why?
When all that happens, then there's no enough people down there to lay in there.
And there's points back to you guys, because there's a lot of people down there getting their
up to two homes, unless they don't have time to do their job.
So, basically, then they changed into where you've got to have an electrician.
Inspecting buildings.
So, I jumped right on it.
I got to man out there.
I paid for three buildings today that didn't have any damage to the wiring.
They didn't have their refinements.
Let's be more precise.
And they were watering them, but in none electrical.
Now, it also was in the house, which got in there and they all passed inspection.
They had been ready to inspect for quite some period of time.
So, we need a plan.
I mean, and stick to it.
I know FEMA gets in the way you guys.
I've seen it before.
There was going straight forward and I asked them, I have no smell.
I said, what's going on, guys?
They were so scattered.
And they said, hey, FEMA, you're going to try to travel with us.
And told them, we have to do that.
Prior to seven.
Just one need in an issue.
Okay.
So, Mr. Mayor.
If I may, with all due respect to my friend here,
this is not a budget discussion.
This was a late day.
I don't know.
11 is flooding discussions, but simply.
And so if they hear and Dean will respond and probably other staff will also about this specifically on that item that the mayor has.
It's something that they need. They're already plus created and your employees are plus created because they're overworked.
And I told somebody a year ago that if you, you know, they said, well look at all these things, guys.
If you don't have these extra men when you have an emergency, you don't have enough to perform and that looks like what I'm saying.
So Kevin, when I'm 11.
Okay. Thank you.
So now let's put it all right.
So that was me.
What now I was banned.
So again, at this time, if there's no other questions about the budgets specifically or comments about the
budget specifically, I'm going to close the public hearing on the budget.
Okay.
Item four is public input and unscheduled personal appearances.
Anyone of the audience who is to address the council on the agenda items set for item 11.
If we'll hold that conversation until that time.
Item five is consent agenda staff is recommending item five items five and six.
Excuse me.
Item six through ten for the consent agenda.
If you take a quick look at those and there are no questions or concerns on any of those.
We will, I would entertain the motion to approve.
I'll let the motion.
And a second please second roll call.
Foreignster.
Hi.
Work it.
All right.
Item 11.
Flood.
Discussion.
We're going to divide a.
Just did a PowerPoint.
I've got a few other things to talk about.
Then I'll be getting to that item without the.
Okay.
Just be.
No, I'm just saying be patient with me.
I will get to this side.
But I've got a few other things that need to kind of bring everybody up to speed on.
And staff is here as well.
Anyway, just wanted to give everybody a kind of an update of where we stand right now and what we're trying to plan to do on recovery.
One thing we just happened today is that a lot of people have been thinking that the April tornado and the May floods.
We're going to be blended into one flood or one disaster declaration.
We found out that they're going to be separate declarations.
Do you know we had a small tornado that went through here on the 30th of April.
So I believe from the 30th of April to about six will be one disaster declaration and the May floods after that will be a second disaster.
A second disaster declaration and all probability because the May floods are going to be a federal disaster for multi state and it's a large thing that we're going to be talking about.
But anybody watching this anybody that's involved one thing.
that we, if you are talking to people, one thing that we're trying to make very clear is that
if anybody has any damage, including damage that might be covered by insurance, see their
tornado or flood, they need to report this to the website www.damaged.ok.gov. Because this,
the type of damage we guess will determine if we get a federal disaster declaration. And
we do think that we've had enough damage to cause that kind of a problem that we've got
to get that information out there. So I'm getting just to clarify, not just the amount,
but actually the nature of the damage and the nature of the damage and the amount. And of
course, one thing that we'll be talking about here is we're keeping track of all of our
cost as well because this is going to be additional costs for us. And we're going to be trying
to work on it and keep things going. But the tornado recovery has been complicated by the flooding.
There's still some isolated area of the roadside tree limbs someplace late by the property
owners. Where the process right now is kind of establishing a cut off to say, you still have
any tornado limb damage, get it out to the road after that. There's just going to have to take
care of it as they normally would. Just as for your information on the small tornado we had,
we've taken care of 741 tons of tree limbs from the tornado. And that's about six hundred and
five tons have been collected just by the street. So just getting an idea of that. And I think with
the flooding that's been happening, we've basically forgotten about the tornado flooding discussion.
We've had roughly 50 homes and 25 businesses, all MSUA customers, including solid waste customers,
per the data we've got. We only think about 15 of those customers have flood policies and have been
impacted by flood water. It's been a question about whether they have flood insurance, they don't have
flood insurance. Some of the larger properties, especially commercial properties in that area, do not have
flood insurance. That we found out. This devolence area, this devolence area primarily. So power has been or will be
restored in this, isn't getting right into what you're talking about now. In buildings that were not or not
significantly inundated by water, we basically were restoring the power. So I'm not entirely sure
we know what the problems are when I want to get the details later. But what we have been working on is that we did pull a lot
of meters when the water was rustling. It was kind of all hell hands on deck, it didn't get in the meters off. Some properties
did not have water in them. We're trying to get the power back on. Our occupied, we take care of it, some
aren't occupied, that might be a problem. What we also were saying is if a property only had just a little
bit of water, a few inches or something like that, did not get into any of the electrical, we were going to be
restoring those as well. So that was our plan. Now going on to the next slide.
If the building has been significantly inundated, and what we're talking about significantly
at the water-covered outlets, there are electrical elements or anything like that,
they do have to be inspected by licensed electrician before we will restore power, and
that's the basic public safety.
And is that any different than the way we did in 2007?
Well, I know you weren't here, I wasn't here in 2007.
How many of you didn't have to have a licensed electrician look at the one panel?
And I think the employee is employed one with all of my couldn't.
Everything is moving to the flow that you think is in the city of electrician, the fillet
that they didn't make it in my electrician.
Well, that right now is out of the city of electrician, but an electrician in the city is the license
of electrician.
Exactly.
So basically, I didn't realize that slide was coming up so quickly.
So that's our plan right now.
So if Christy's right behind you, and we're trying to get that inspection done, I'm trying to understand
what your concerns were because this is what our staff has been trying to get.
So if it wasn't inundated, you don't have to have an inspection, we'll get it back up and run.
My thinking is when I forgot the thing, I'm going to be getting me understanding the thing
and free food water with this primary one.
But they basically, we need to get something organized where we can get continuity.
And at this point, we pull them all off, and it's the equivalent of, all right, let's say gas service company.
I just had to pay a electrician to come out with the buildings that the electric boat was not even cut.
Because the city didn't have a man to send up the truck in a timely manner.
And it was cheaper for me to pay electrician.
That's the equivalent of gas service company, come out and say, hey, that might not be right.
I'm going to pay five dollars for you to turn your pot of water on.
And as a vendor, if any of you guys are there, if they've formed the way that things have been going, you guys would fire them in a heartbeat.
Now that's my opinion, don't get paid for it.
So, how can I help?
You know, I don't want you to have good people left there.
Let's get them more out of this line.
And a lot of them, in business with them, they're not happy with the way things are going.
And I think you guys need to figure out a way to make them work better for you.
And they lose them good people.
And that's, you know, I didn't really ask for it.
I've been calling them all the different people.
It hasn't been going all the way.
Anyway, it's obviously a crime time for me to not appreciate your patience.
Do you have questions from me?
I do.
This is, you know, you've made notion that you've talked to a few of our city employees.
Is this something that has been going on prior to flooding?
Are you strictly talking about the flooding situation?
Have a case and, you know, you leave it when they're all over the place.
You know, I've talked to probably in different city employees.
Is this during the flooding situation?
No.
Okay.
But I know a lot of you in the name.
You know what I mean?
I just want to make sure I just want to know if it is strictly flooding.
The situation that we're having and how do we correct that or what is our protocol?
And, you know, I agree with you when I'm percent.
I don't, we don't want to lose good employees if they're tired or wore out.
I just want to make sure that if it's flooding event that is causing these individuals
that you're talking about to be upset or wore out, we need to figure out what our plan is to actually do.
Do I?
Grab them off.
You know, COVID-19.
No, that's fine.
I don't want you to.
I don't want to know what your plan is.
I don't want to lose your name.
I don't want to know.
Right.
Because I do know there's coming down there tonight.
And, anyway, I don't normally, if I complain, I've got an answer.
I think my thought is, mind the floods.
We know we're going to flood.
We know we're going to flood again.
Have a set.
I don't have a problem if you're going to have to pay an electrician.
Although, that I can afford it.
It's an extreme hardship on some of them.
But at first, I was on a good question.
Because I attend, they don't call the water to my house and said, what do you want?
And they said, well, that comes your house.
If the water got in, the outlets, if they're good and clean, we'll go ahead and meet you back up.
Otherwise, you're going to have to replace them.
And then, in a couple of three days, you just like after seven, five, things changed.
And they were overwhelmed.
And they couldn't get out and look at it.
And then, finally, I have to circle by these ones.
And that fire came out in the last couple of days that you're going to have to get to the electrician.
Which I would gladly pay to be able to get back to working on things.
Because I have a commercial convertible.
And that tore a little bit went to the city, went diagonally from my place,
break over to my house.
And then come in the pan, which I probably got more debris on the ground after I think that's it.
But anyway, I'm trying to clean and extend it.
I'm trying to ask for that.
But you get to play in a place ahead of time.
A pitch can be set to stone ever time.
The last few times it's been changing.
And it's, you know, people are on it anyway.
And then they came.
And I did not get continuity from one office to the front window.
Now, people will help them.
But if they go, it was going sideways.
And maybe it was because I didn't explain myself well.
And maybe it wasn't, I don't know.
But in the end, most of them are very helpful and they're passionate.
But I don't think they've got the manpower.
was your HFAC system affected? Was your HFAC system under water as well? HVRC? You're air conditioner
on the edge because that would need to be as hot water tank if it's on the floor level too. I know where you live
and you get it about every flood. It's up in your house.
It's the entities and the not being able to, you know, you can't, they don't have the
manpower to respond well and this is a small flood compared to 770.
There's hardly any of the houses left.
So, Dean, I know you were still kind of in the midst of the flood recovery part, but I assume that a few weeks
out you and staff will convene a meeting and you'll talk about what went well and what didn't
work and we do better. Actually, we were having meetings right now.
I would avoid some of the things that I was talking about. It's what I'll guarantee that.
That's what this is. Thanks, Alan.
The second item on that slide. Would you address that, Dean?
I definitely would. As I said, these are all, everybody that we know is that's involved
is an MSUA customer which also includes solid waste.
So, we're going to be providing solid waste clean up.
Including for commercial customers, because they are our customers as well.
We do collect solid waste from them.
And we're trying to get that taken care very quickly.
And again, what we're talking about is we're going to be bringing in some additional assistance.
We're going to be hiring folks as well.
That will be covered by the federal disaster declaration.
But we've got to do the clean up fairly quickly.
Go by some of the hotels. You already see mattresses that are out of the stream.
We can't leave those out for a long period of time.
People are taking out sheetrock. People are taking out carpet.
This is all stuff that our solid waste can handle.
But it's just a matter of getting it out.
So, we're making plans to be able to take care of that.
We're back that just a minute to the first item because of something you just said.
When I was talking, one of the things that was going through my head is when the tornado came through or whenever we have a disaster.
from other communities that didn't suffer a disaster will come in and help is are we able to just bring in I'm just going to say regular
electricians because I don't know how to describe it. They could help with the inspections and things like that and if we have a flood
a disaster declaration build that back then to I think I think I could. I wasn't aware we were having problems getting
electricians end to be able to do these inspection pluses we were saying this we have basically 50 houses and 25
businesses. I think part of ours point is that he can afford to pay an electrician if he needs you to
get it down but some of our residents can and so they would be relying on our staff to do that work and then
because we have 50 or plus and keep in mind by code we cannot do that kind of work. So we would have to have
a licensed electricity kind of inspection. So let's let's get on that. But they could visit the
building and look and say the water didn't get enough to get into the water. That work we're supposed to
be now like you can't even do that. Because there's not enough manpower what you're saying. I don't know why but
I don't know. You're just saying it's not happening and you do other assumptions. Okay. All right thanks
out. So on the I've got a couple of comments on the next item I've heard from a couple of people
one person called me and was frustrated because we were going to provide free dumpsters to people
and they felt like it was the city going into competition with the private business and I said I would share
that in fact I called and then I had another business been that is on Steve Owen's call me and say
I heard you're not going to provide dumpsters that's not fair you hauled off everybody's storm
debris from the tornado why won't you help us with this and I said let I think it's going to be
a topic of the meeting tonight. So we'll let you know tomorrow exactly what's going to happen at our
tent is to hold. Okay. And the rationale for that so we have an answer for the gym and it was concerned about
the city competing with him is that because what he said to me specifically was those are my tax dollars
you're using to compete with me and I understand this point of view but from our perspective those are
our customers that are also they're paying not only taxes but they're also paying in SUVA fees. Correct.
And there's a health and safety issue. Yeah. I'm getting that. Very good. Very good. Very good.
Very good. Exactly. Anybody on that slide? Anybody have any other comments?
Any council member? Okay lean. That's all that. Okay the other thing that this is probably
something that we're going to get a lot of people in here to talk to you about. But we fully
intended to follow the theme of regulations regarding the 50% and just kind of a 15%.
explanation. That means many of the properties whose damage to recovery equals 50% of the
depreciated value of the structure cannot be rebuilt unless they meet all FEMA regulations.
And that includes building above the 100 year base flood elevation. And these properties are
going to be considered red tag. So, Dean is at the depreciated value or the current value.
What I have read is the depreciated value is how FEMA goes. This is a 15-second explanation.
This is a very detailed process that we're going to have to go through and kind of looking at
Chris because he's going to be one of the people that's going to be very involved with it. But it is
one of the FEMA regulations about that. I know you were doing that in 2007. Yeah, I'd seem like in
2007 that people were able to, if they wanted to go to the expense of getting an appraisal,
they could use that value. That same, that's what the law said. I think that that happened
on something like that. So, I would just be curious to you know that we want to clarify that the other
part, and maybe you're going to get there, but that's actually a cumulative number. It's not just this
highlighted. As I understand the regulations, if they had 25% of the value last time around and
there's 30% this time, that's 55% and they would be red tag. So, we'd probably need to be clear on that.
We'd want to be very clear on that. And that is commercial properties, commercial and residential
correct. And for the benefit of people that may be watching, this is not something that the city
of a rural city put in place. If we don't follow these guidelines, then our community cannot participate
in a national flood insurance program. We're potentially not received federal assistance for recovery.
Right. So, it's crucial that we are members and, again, I know some of the other council members
have probably participated. We have to, we have to pass audiences from time to time to stay in compliance
in order to participate in NFIP, you know. Go ahead, Dean. Okay. Next up. Now, other thing, this is probably
going to be a little different from 2007 as well. In the normal conditions, the property owner could appeal
or write tags as a nation to the Board of Adjustment. But we don't really have a planning and Board of Adjustment
right now because we're redoing the ordinance that establish them. So, I just wanted to make you aware
that any appeals are going to be heard directly to you. I thought you'd appreciate that slide.
Take my credit for that. Yeah. Step up and take credit for that.
Take a credit for that. Well, it is what it is. We also, I think, just to do this whole thing, we've got to
recognize that, you know, just as Allison, this is not nearly as big a Float of 2007. We've got communities all up
and down the earth.
I can saw River Basin that have had major flooding.
Of course, you know, I used to work in Fort Smith.
I still have friends there.
I'm going to touch with them.
They said at least 500 homes they were in a data.
I know that Governor Hutchison in Fort Smith,
or in what's in Fort Smith at the end of the day,
and just asking people would be to please be patient.
This is tough all over.
So I think this is something that even when we're working with the state,
we're probably going to be toward the end of the line in some way.
I look at the problems in Tulsa.
You look at places like Moffitt, Weber's Falls that are just almost completely washed out.
It looks like we had our time in 2007.
They're having their time now.
This is a major natural disaster that we're dealing with.
Moving on to the next.
At highlights, why we've been strongly involved with the real licensing of Pensacola.
And the problems we've had with the operations by GRDA and the core of engineers.
And why we've been, you know, so involved, you know,
with both legally, from an administrative standpoint.
We think we need to continue to push for pre-releases prior to predicted range
to increase rates of our storage capacity.
We're collecting information on that right now.
When this started, the lake was at 751 by the real curve by 1st,
should have been at 743.
And obviously, our attorneys are taking a look at this.
Obviously, our hydrologists are taking a look at that.
We also believe that with all the other cities that are experiencing this flooding,
Brian, you kind of highlighted a video on a Tulsa World that was very interesting.
We think these other cities are going to start understanding where our problems have been
and start asking for a review of the way the core of engineers operates in stands.
And I think this ties into a lot of the work we've done over the last year.
This is almost a textbook example in my mind.
So something to keep in mind is we go on.
Go on to the next.
We're going to continue to push GRDA to acquire proper flood easements.
On this point, the city we're going to actively seek funds to acquire demolished properties,
which have had repetitive flood.
This follows the guidelines contained in the city's comprehensive plan.
Mayors, you just indicated that this becomes a repetitive and competitive situation.
I understand that there are some people who have been flooded to say that they don't want to move on.
They don't want to have this happen to them again.
We have a situation where water is going to go, where water is going to go,
and we really have to start looking at this, but those people need to be compensator for their properties.
And again, we have some major lawsuits dealing with this and the losses that people have had
because of this and what we feel is that the backwater effect of grain lake and the fact that GRDA does not have proper easements.
We're also going to continue to lobby ODOT to provide funding to elevate those Steve Owens Boulevard in 69 messed up the river.
And again, all of these writings that we have had in the compound, we've been lobbying for,
but it becomes very evident why we need to do that.
We do have flood insurance, and we're in the process of making damage claims for city facilities and potential reimbursement for our flooding cost.
We're also accounting for all cost and anticipation of federal reimbursement under disaster declaration.
There are going to be community effects we're going to have to deal with, odor, increase of mosquitoes, displaced wildlife, flood debris.
We're going to be working with the Health Department related actions that are since should take to protect themselves.
And again, but I was talking about there, we're going to need additional assistance.
We're probably going to hire some additional people to help us with electric recovery, allowing staff to continue to concentrate on normal operations during this time.
This was an inconvenience but it's kind of concentrated.
The other things in town we also need to continue to work on.
So again along that line, that is what we're going to be trying to do.
We're going to be we'll probably talk about this issue with the electricians after this meeting since it was brought up.
That's what this discussion was supposed to do is help us with ideas along that line.
Okay.
As conditions allow facilities such as the bald diamonds will be reopened once they can be utilized.
Brian, I know you've got a lot of calls about things like that.
Yeah, I have a few words to say.
You know, there's always a concern in making sure that we, you know, our youth have a place to go and play.
And it affects my kids and everything else.
But I just want people to stop and look and I appreciate it.
I talked to Kevin Browning today.
I appreciate him taking the extra steps to make sure that allowing kids back out onto the fields and in the facilities.
What are the protocols and I think that some of the things we're talking to Kevin is, and I believe I've asked somebody else to do.
In 2007, what was the steps to mail when we get back out there?
What are, where's it written down there?
Did he might make vlogs and so far nobody can find anything.
So Kevin is really going to try to put something in place so we can follow that guideline for say just for that.
So I understand that flood affects everybody in every different way.
To some people that didn't flood their houses or their businesses or work.
It's, it's making just getting their kids to back into it.
And it's a very minute problem.
But when people start taking and worrying about the facilities, in my opinion, of revenue, getting more than getting kids back out into a safe, healthy place to play.
I really struggled with that. So I've had some conversations and I wish the conversation started.
You know, what is it safe for the kids to be out there and that was not the case.
So first and foremost, for my standpoint setting up here, I appreciate what the city has done as far as making sure and call.
contacting the right people to say you know what we are good let's get you can go ahead
and start cleaning up and doing that before just saying yeah go ahead and go after and do
whatever you need to do to get your games played and so I appreciate Kevin for taking that extra
step. One of the things that you mentioned will go and it's talking about the roads and backing
up a little bit and there might be something but you know it was asked to me I know we always talked
about Steve Owens but that's something I think we need to consider as you know and everybody
faced it to try to get through town and what other roads you know 20 second was a lifeline there
for for a long time and then it became it went under and then we had to go all the way through
commerce so I think that as a council we need to consider what is if Steve Owens is going to
be down the road what is our other option is there is there a way that we can raise 20 second or something
down the road and I believe we need to be good stewards with the county and I visited with
Mike Farmas who thought he was that area that I was in talking about was 20 second going out to
the mushroom from road because that road really starts to take on flash flood and then it's deteriorating
so there's a bunch of things that in the roads aspect that I think we need to think about what can we
do to kind of help people get in and out of town just a little bit better down the road so
you mentioned the mosquito spreading and I don't know if that falls underneath it you know where we
set up to handle that we normally you know you can we can do some mosquitoes spreading but with this amount
of water is right hard to know how effective it's going to be right the best thing to do is get some
off right now not having any standing water but even when the water receives remember we want to be
talking about this in a minute or every park has been underwater for a minute so when it does
receive we're still going to have standing water, puddles and there's all sorts of things we can do
we're talking earlier about we don't have enough cakes to throw into all the problems we're going to have
so it's just going to be a little bit of everything one other thing is you talk about roads and I'm
putting it in a flooding discussion was a bridge project that they were working on out there you know
I knew we had a kind of a timeline and I saw some of the drone footage and saw them pushed all
their equipment the best they could up to the last spot I'm assuming they didn't lose anything or
hopefully heard of is it push or it's so back I've not heard of anything that's pushed at that
no it is it we feel okay that we're still moving along right and that is but they actually
rebounded on our lot right I knew they moved a bunch of stuff I just didn't know if this is going to
push their time and then when we talked to them they didn't seem to thank you for the fact that
okay when you talk about some of the areas being down for so long they had to completely
stop for all that time, so I just was curious.
I'm being honest with you.
I just wanted to hitchhike on Brown's comments about the safety of the ball parks.
I don't know if most people understand that we had to bypass our source plant.
Totally.
We had to bypass ours, but other communities have streamed bypassed theirs.
That's exactly the thing.
It's not just river water or like water out there.
It's polluted water.
Yeah.
And that was the discussion I had.
You know, there was a thing that I read, well, we've all played in the river around here.
And really, we're not talking about the same stuff when you're talking about the torque
creek.
And then you're talking about all the pollution's in.
And so I had that discussion with the individuals.
And then they really, I kind of understand what you're saying.
So when Congress and Mullins came to do his two or Debbie Dooley, who was a former Miami
who was with him in 86, her son got a staff infection from getting out on the football field two
points.
Soon after, in a couple of other players, I mean, they can, you know, it can really be a bad deal.
We're trying to be careful about that.
And we're also trying to make sure that once once you're safe, we get them back into operation
because a lot of people are looking for it.
And to hit track on that, we do have action and a plan and it's just timing it as crazy as it sounds
my understanding is, as if we had a little bit of rain, it sure does come off in a way.
Oh, we're also telling you, you're saying rain and sunshine.
sunshine and rain.
Yeah.
We're sunshine and rain.
We have a monster truck showing three weeks.
We hope we can get a taking place.
We might have to be taking a look at alternative parking for it.
Maybe even utilize state highway 125 since the bridges are closed.
But, you know, that's one of our biggest customers for the arena.
We might have that done.
I think they'd like to continue to have it.
But that's just one of the issues we're talking about.
Going on to the next.
We strongly are considering relocating this year's independent state celebration.
Exactly for Brian, which he was just talking about.
We have a few parts been underwater for over a month.
And we're not sure if it would be in the shape to handle any kind of the hundreds of visitors
that they enjoyed the event.
Just today, pointed out that some of our people are indicating that we're the waters receiving
that you have things like fishing hooks and things like that.
And let alone, you know, what we're talking about this being not just river water, but basically
some raw sewage that's combined.
So just since this is such a big event for this community, we're thinking about trying to find
another orientation forward.
So we're working on that right now.
Why don't you be aware?
We're also uncertain when we can open the mind and miss a pool that they get in the water, we
had to remove our pumps.
And then the splash pad is going to be delayed due to chronic rains as well.
So that's just, in fact, matter, we don't know how much it's going to be delayed, but I think
the best thing to do is anticipate this going to be just because of all the rain we've
had.
Is that due to in-house work or is it?
Contractor company?
It's all contract.
I put some of the videos that we've produced,
the marketing videos, and then the video with the 2018
year-end year review, and then we also included
their some videos that we use to market our industrial building
and our industrial park, and also the careful.
So that's on the flash drive.
Along the way, I've included two folders with documents
that are full copies of the last two proposals
that we've prepared competing for new jobs
through the commerce department.
So all that is there.
It just gives you some good examples of the work
that we're doing, and a lot of good information.
So we wanted to give that to you.
The report that I've put together, I tried to format that
in a way that would be kind of broad topics.
And if you have any questions or things
that you want to talk about, I'm preparing.
I wanted to kind of touched on a little bit of the end
of 2018 and then 2019 year today.
So many of you have visited our offices down on Main Street,
and it's a behind-the-back activity.
A lot of really positive feedback from visitors and others.
There's pretty much generally the comment is, wow,
I can't believe this is here in Miami.
So that's a very positive thing.
And it's a great place to work with.
We feel blessed to be in there.
But it's a real hub of energy and activity.
In late 18 and early 2019, the main chamber boards
put together a revision to the bylaws.
When we started this almost three years ago,
we amended the bylaws, and then we realized
that they weren't where these congruent all the way through.
And so we really rolled up our sleeves and went to work
to make those really work together well,
because we still maintain two nonprofit corporations.
There's the main nonprofit corporation.
And then there's the chamber non-profit corporation.
We maintain separate books, separate financials.
And there's one board that they change to have,
like you all do.
One meaning is the chamber, the next meaning is the main board.
So the part I want to make about the bylaws of ignorance
is that we added interior board seats in the bylaws.
And so we are more talked about this a lot.
And if there are people who are interested and want
to get more engaged and want to be involved
in economic development and chamber commerce
to a great detail, we would love to have people come forward
to join the board, and we have some seats that are available.
So it's wanted to let you all know that.
And please pass along any buddy who's interested.
that it comes to trying to bring you industry in.
And so thank you for that.
And Dean, and I work very close together.
Tyler's always involved and many other things that.
So the first local incentive is the fact
that we have a very cooperative city,
and that we are a utility provider that will make things happen.
Instead of throwing up barriers and trouble.
At the state level, we have a wide range of incentives
from the state.
Most of those are tax related.
So we always put together very closely with the commerce department
and put together an incentive proposal for the state
of Oklahoma.
And that's based on several things.
One is the number of new jobs and the wages,
the amount of investment, the kind of industry that it is,
and does the company provide benefits to its employees.
So those are the state level incentives.
And then the last piece of incentives are the federal incentives.
Where qualified is called federal new market tax credits.
So if a company comes in and they invest $5 million
in a new bill, if they do new market tax credits
through these tax credits from the federal government,
they can get $1 million of additional cash
or 20% of their capital investment.
And that comes at the beginning of their project.
So that's a big deal.
If you're invested in 10 million, you can get 2 million.
There aren't a lot of places in the country
that have that incentive.
There are a lot of places, not all of them know how to use.
And we're using it.
And always propose a new market tax credits.
The second one is, in 2018, after the Trump administration
approved a tax bill, there was a new program
that was started by the tax bill
and it's called opportunity zones.
So I've read about that.
And I wrote a letter and put a package together,
promoting Ottawa County and our census tracks,
to be designated by the governor as an opportunity zone.
We eventually, through that process,
we got three of our census tracks.
A, all of our North County border, all of our East County border,
and then coming kind of in the middle there
where the industrial park is, and then industrial,
we're all in opportunity zone.
What an opportunity zone does.
If you have an investor that has a capital gains occurrence,
they can avoid paying federal capital gains tax by investing
in an opportunity zone.
And so we're set up to offer that tool
and that investment opportunity for companies
that are located.
So federal opportunities zone.
And then the last federal incentive that we have
is we are a, it gives companies an advantage
when they are competing for federal contracts.
And that is called, and I'm spaced out on that.
But that's called.
We're that too, so if you do federal contracting and you locate an audible county, you can get significant advantages by low community.
So, that is, our incentive is a major positive for us.
The other thing, I'll say, if we partner very closely, I mentioned the workforce development.
Very closely with Ineo and very closely with Northeast T.
And we talked about this earlier this week.
Last week, we had our board meeting.
The fact that our school district and our citizens approved the bond issue for our schools,
that is a major statement that this community made to the positive,
saying that we support our young people, that education is important,
and that directly relates to the, but eventually the quality of our workforce.
And I think too, that what that does is it tells people that might be considering coming here,
that as a community, we invest, we're investing in our schools, we're investing in our young people.
And so, those are all big advantages for locating our industrial party.
I'll say one of our biggest challenges is that we have the 54,000 square foot spectrum.
Now, that's an advantage in that when I ride proposals, we always companies and the reason you build a spectrum is because it's there.
And you can move quickly, we can move quickly, and we can accommodate your relocation or your expansion, very quickly.
And so, we continue to market the spectrum.
And I'll tell you that the outside of having a spectrum is that there's a cost in carrying the debt on that boat.
And so, we're paying for that, that out of our operating resources and try to be creative about that,
working with the local banks.
But one of the biggest challenges that I want to try to resolve, hopefully, with a site visitor,
that visitor too, we might get a field going, but we need to get that spectrum ill in salt.
What are we setting on? How long have we had this thing now setting their empty?
But when I came in 2016, excuse me, the fall of 2016, it was under construction.
And we finished it up in the fall into the winter of 2016.
So we've been we've been marking it for all of 17, all of 18, and now 19 year today.
So as long as I've been here, we've been marching that spectrum and carrying it.
And so it is, I think about that every day.
The end really done.
We think about it every day.
So that's the big thing, if we can get somebody in that spectrum building and get that carry,
but carry costs.
off of us, then we're going to be in a lot better shape, but plus it would be new jobs and
new investment.
You talk about opportunities zones.
Is this something that comes and goes or once it's an opportunity zone you're there
forever?
Well, so it's based on the designation is a census tract.
So we have three census tract that until the federal government changes it, it'll be that way.
And so in any company that's located in that area and our entire industrial part and really
most of the land along the 69A is opportunity zones.
There are numerous tribal entities that are in opportunity zones and the big challenge
that we have right now is that we're waiting on the IRS and the Treasury Department
to give us the rules about how opportunity zones work.
So we're watching that, monitoring that, but let me, I'll try to be not too much in the
weeds, but so let's say that an individual or a company has a capital gains of permits and
their subject to pay capital A gains tax, but the opportunity zone does is they can take that
money and they can put it into an opportunity fund and that's easy to create.
That's no problem creating opportunity fund.
Once it's in an opportunity fund, that money can be used as a way to purchase real estate or
to fund the operations of a company located in the opportunity zone.
And if that investment stays in that company for, I think, 10 years plus or minus, what happens
is the basis, the IRS is just the basis that was the basis for the gain is adjusted up and
you don't have a tax liability.
Then you can take your money back out and you didn't pay capital gains.
So it's very complicated, there's not a lot of clear rules or regulations about it, but
in an F shell, it has to do with capital gains and reinvesting it in the zone.
And they won't go away until the federal government ordered change.
Potentially, they could change the tax law on five years, that was a way to, they're trying
to steal capital towards the press, Eric.
That's right.
And all of these federal programs I talked about are New Market Tax Trends, Optisms.
They were done with the intention to bring new jobs and new investment into economically depressed
areas by census trend.
So that's the idea.
New Market Tax Trends is very, very crude and why it's important is program opportunities
zones, hopefully we will gain some traction.
And so the bad news is we qualify for them, the good news is we qualify for them.
That's exactly right.
Yeah.
Okay.
On the 169A, just as in the office today, and I got a visit, and they are now actively acquiring right away.
So that was a good sign.
Yeah.
And the industrial part has some right away that they're going to just pay us for.
The question is, I'd be happy to visit with anybody individually.
Just give me a call, drop me an email, and I'll come to you and we can unpack as much of this as you're interested in that.
No, and I probably will.
That was, it's always tough.
And I think I've said it every time you've done this.
What you do is not an easy job.
Everybody I give is like, what are they doing?
What are we doing with the spectrum?
Why do we keep them money?
What do we get out of it?
Yeah.
So I have to, and I always told you this.
I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I was really, you know, we have to have something because we've got
A lot of side organizations that we give them credits for stuff, and they, they have a plan, and they got a thing they got to go through.
So sure.
My request, and in, and I appreciate she putting this together is, you know, you always look at it and I was telling her,
I, you know, that don't have my paper from last year because I always like to see what what your goals were and where you were last year.
What you hope for and where's that at this year?
And then so I, I'm going to try to make it better out for it to keep in this.
And because, you know, how do you regulate what, what do you consider successful?
I mean, is it selling the spec building or finding somebody in that that's a successful year?
I don't know.
And you know, and I'll tell you, I think success is, you know,
a big part of it is the fact that in Oklahoma City, the Commerce Department and elected officials, they know that we're ready for business here.
And we, we think, bring a project here.
They know that we know how to work it and we'll make it work.
We make it happen.
Yeah.
And I think we had an opportunity, and it just didn't go our way.
And I think if that would have worked out, we would have all been, we'd all been heroes.
And no one would ever say anything.
And that's where I try to remind people that, you know, it, like you said, it's a tea or a ton of one minute.
It looks great.
And next minute, everything falls off from the earth.
That's right.
And I, I, the lab put it is in economic development.
You do have kids a lot of frauds.
And when I say we have nine active projects, three of those are local.
And six of those are, we've submitted a very good proposal for it.
And one of those six, we're going to have a site visit.
And so when we get a site visit, I think we show well.
And that's what I'm hoping for.
building work? Well, reasonably priced. Well, and it is. We're open to least purchase options on that building.
If you've got that building for us, cheaper than the new kind of building.
That's true. That one. That one. That's true.
Thank you. Thank you.
Any other questions for Steve?
Thanks Steve. Thank you very much for that.
Item 13, fiscal year 2018, 19, municipal budget, message and resolution regarding the city of Miami.
Budget for the 2019, 2020 year and establishing budget amendment authority.
Jill.
I'm just here to answer questions.
I think that has been from our budget session meeting.
I can't tell you that the two outside organizations you asked me to contact,
that we had received applications, I did and I got application.
So is this just an updated, are we always being asked to vote on the budget?
You were being asked to vote on the budget.
And Vicki's not here, but she had text when she said she was going to make it.
I've made sure she knew we were going to be voting on the budget tonight and ask her if that was a concern.
She said, no, go right ahead.
So we're still good.
We're not having to transfer.
Did you close the gap on what you were?
Yes.
So where we had currently on that?
So the general fund, right, man.
Well, the money, I did exactly what I said I would do.
We actually changed a little bit on the street,
been alley fund and the street stadium fund.
So of the additional money that we collect,
we can choose to use that for over here or use 240,000 of that for over here.
Street alley, you can have 260,000.
So that's a 500,000.
That's the whole thing.
With that getting in at 2D, how will the flooding in the tornado affect our budget?
That's right now.
That's why it's so important to get all the damage in.
That if we get a federal disaster declaration, we'll look at it.
I'm just curious how we're going to pay for it.
It's there if we need it.
That's our worst case scenario.
Yeah.
It's a good answer.
Which is a good answer.
One of those applications that you were seeing the tear that we were supposed to go on.
Did they give you an audit as well?
Or is it like the financials?
They usually give it.
Yeah.
They present our financials are recorded.
They may not be audited financials.
I don't think you're funny.
I don't think you're funny at all.
Do you enjoy your transactions?
Probably gets an audit daily.
How do they?
I don't know if all of them do.
We don't get audits.
We don't get the financials.
Some organizations are required by law and a half.
But then we can ask that.
Yeah.
Any concerns about approving the budget tonight?
And we still have a little bit of time, but if we don't have any concerns, we'll move forward
if there are concerns, if Vicki didn't have any, but anybody.
I'm good.
No, I think my only concern was, and I've always stressed that is, is when I will be put
in there to not transfer.
Yeah.
And that's where we're good, where we're not having to.
We're a little bit in there.
So, we have a motion to approve of item 13, which is a universal budget, ready?
Message and resolution, and establishing budget amendment authority.
And a second.
Second.
Roll call, please.
Work it.
All right.
Four.
Thank you, everyone.
Item 14 through 16, I look like they're related to the conversations we had earlier.
Is that fair to say?
Great.
Okay.
And if you'll just briefly describe each one again, then we'll.
So, that part of the number 14 is the clean water, state of volume.
And so, that is, it's sewer, paint case sewer, and it's from sewer stuff.
Thank you.
I'm just trying to see there's, so there's not in the, in the S.U.A. agenda items that were dollar
amounts listed.
I don't know if they have to be here.
I'm just, I'm not making.
Okay.
But, don't need to come up.
That, please.
Hey, that was public finance logger, but the question, I think you're thinking about asking
it, is why are we approving this again?
The authority is the issuer of the debt.
So, you've already taken action to approve the issuance of each of these three nodes under
the public trust statutes for Oklahoma.
The city has been a fisher of the public trust.
It's required to approve the actions taken by the authority.
So, each of these resolutions is individually approving each of the issuance of node by the
authority.
And so, that's why these don't have to be quite as specific.
There's the U.S. U.A. because they were going out, approving, barring of specific amounts
and we're just approving their actions, right?
Okay.
Any other questions?
If not, do we have a most to approve item 14, most to approve?
And the second, please?
Second.
What would we call?
One, two, four, sir.
All right.
Work it.
Sure.
All right.
I will make a motion to approve item 15, which is authorizing the issuance.
The MSUA is action authorizing the issuance.
We have a second.
We'll call, please.
Solve.
All right.
Work it.
Four, sir.
All right.
And item 16 is action with respect to the resolution, approving the action taken by the
MSUA.
specifically the drinking water SRF promissory note for the OWRB. We have most of you
have pretty wide of 16.
And a second.
Second.
The roll call please.
First.
I want to thank you gentlemen.
If Tyler had done a better job either had that earlier in the agenda.
I know you probably have a long drive, but Blank Tyler not me.
I am 17 as new business.
Any new business?
Anyone?
I am 18 as staff reports.
I'm a picture in your packet.
That's available if there are any questions on anything.
I am 19 as mayor and council committee announcements in the announcements.
Anyone?
I just will say on behalf of the council, we do appreciate all the hours and time and effort
staff is put into this and in some ways the hardest part still to come.
We talk about the red tagging and all that kind of stuff.
That's not going to be any fun.
We're going to have some people angry.
We're going to set up to deal with it.
Any other announcements?
I am 20 as city manager communication.
Make everything I need to be covered.
I covered over Floor.
I am 21 as a German.
We have most of you in German.
Thanks.
And a second.
Second.
Roll call please.